Leonard Eck Papers
Austin History Center, Austin Public Library
Leonard Eck Papers
1882-1949
1882-1914
Eck, Leonard
AR.1992.023
0.4 linear feet ( 1 box )
Austin History Center, Austin Public Library, 810 Guadalupe, PO Box 2287, Austin, TX 78768
Leonard T. Eck and his family (including son Alvin A. Eck) came to Austin from Cedar Falls, Iowa, in the late 1870s and established himself as a local businessman. The collection consists of records dating from 1882 to 1949 concerning Eck's real estate holdings and businesses as well as some personal legal materials and a few items belonging to other family members.
Biographical Note
Leonard Eck, originally from Germany, moved to Austin, Texas, with his wife Francis and children in the late 1870s from Cedar Falls, Iowa. The 1900 Federal Census lists his age as fifty-five. Upon arrival he purchased a jewelry and mercantile business from Sweeney and Combs and the family lived above the store at 101 East 6th Street. An advertisement from 1887 lists him as a "Collateral Broker". Later he had a business on 1200 South Congress Avenue, which, according to the November 27, 1938 American Statesman, was the first store building in South Austin. Eck died in 1925.
Teck, Texas, in western Travis County, was named after Leonard T. Eck, who became postmaster when a post office was established there in 1900. The Teck post office operated until 1919, and again from 1925 to 1929, when it was discontinued and mail for the community was routed through Cedar Valley.
Sources: Austin History Center Biography file and Vivian Elizabeth Smyrl, "TECK, TX," Handbook of Texas Online (http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/hwt01), accessed June 18, 2014. Uploaded on June 15, 2010. Published by the Texas State Historical Association.
Scope and Contents
The majority of the Leonard Eck Papers concerns the business and real estate dealings of Leonard Eck. The Leonard Eck series (1882-1914) consists of business records such as an account book that lists loans made and collateral received in return; promissory notes; correspondence concerning payments dues; account charges; business licenses and legal documents (Deeds Under Order of Sale, Bills of Cost and Deeds from the Sheriff). Real estate materials include Warranty Deeds, General Land Office payment certificates, Abstracts of Title and correspondence. His work as a "collateral broker" and his real estate investments sometimes overlapped as customers occasionally used land as collateral.
In addition to the Leonard Eck documents there are a few items attributed to other members of the family. This series (1914, 1949, undated) includes Henry Eck's South Austin High School report card, adoption papers allowing Henry Eck to adopt the three children of his brother Alvin and his wife Agnes and a certificate of registry for a boar purchased by a relation of Mrs. Jennie Stewart (daughter of Leonard, sister to Henry and Alvin).
Arrangement
Arranged into two series:
I. Leonard Eck
II. Other Family Members
Related Material
Austin Files Biography - Eck, Leonard (although the majority of the material references Alvin Eck)
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Eck, Leonard T., 1849-1925.; Eck, Alvin A., 1874-1970.; Eck, Henry.; Eck, Alvin, L.; Eck, Leonard R.; Eck, Maggie.; Warner, George.
Organizations:
Lakeside Improvement Company.
Places:
Austin (Tex.)--Social life and customs.; Austin (Tex.)--Commerce.; Martin County (Tex.); Teck (Tex.)
Subjects:
Pawnbroker--Texas--Austin.; Real property--Texas--Austin.
Document Types
Deeds
Restrictions on Access
Open to all users.
Custodial History
All but one item in the collection were donated by the daughter of Leonard Eck in 1992. The "Stockman's Pocket Bills of Sale and Memorandum Book" was purchased by the Austin History Center from Kenston Rare Books in 2014.
Acquisition Information
Donor #: DO/1992/096
Donation Date: 1992
Detailed Description of the Collection
- I. Leonard Eck - Professional, 1882-1914
  - Account book - loans made/collateral received, 1882-1884 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Promissory notes, 1885-1886 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence concerning payments due, 1883-1889 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Account charges, 1891-1894 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Business licenses, 1894-1897 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Legal documents - Deeds Under Order of Sale, Bills of Cost and Deeds from the Sheriff, 1887-1897 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Real estate documents - Martin County land, 1884-1894 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Real estate documents - Austin land, 1893-1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Real estate documents - Teck land, 1905-1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Real estate Warranty Deeds - Lakeside Improvement Company, Eck's Heights and others, 1883-1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- II. Other Family Members, 1914, 1949, undated
  - Adoption papers, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Henry Eck report cart, circa 1905 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Certificate of Registry for a boar, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 13)